Finding Aid for the Douglas Edward Leach Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Douglas Edward Leach Papers
1950’s-1994
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0253
5.46 linear feet
Scope and Content Note
The Douglas Edward Leach Papers, 1950’s-1994, include correspondence, class notes and teaching materials, lectures, materials pertaining to professional organizations and activities, manuscripts of writings, and research materials. The thirteen boxes of this collection cover approximately 5.46 linear feet. Theses materials are arranged in five series and encompass the years of Dr. Leach’s professional career as a professor of history. As a group, these papers present a clear picture of a university professor’s life, including teaching, research, writing, committee work, and involvement in professional activities beyond the classroom and the university.
The largest part of the collection, Series I, contained in five boxes, consists of correspondence. It is arranged alphabetically by correspondent’s last names and, following Dr. Leach’s filing pattern, letters to and from him and the letters in reply, are grouped together as they were sent or received in chronological order. Of particular interest is his correspondence with Alexander Heard and Samuel Eliot Morison.
Series II, in two boxes, is a collection of Dr. Leach’s class notes, exams, and resource materials used in his classroom teaching.
Series III, in one box, consists of lectures, both in outline and in manuscript from. Dr. Leach presented these lectures to professional and community groups between 1951 and 1994.
Series IV, in two boxes, is a collection of materials pertaining to Dr. Leach’s involvement in professional organizations, such as the American Historical Association. It also contains materials dealing with his direction of the Vanderbilt-in-England program. Particularly interesting is his correspondence with David B. Quinn, the British historian, concerning Quinn’s honorary membership in the American Historical Association.
Series V, in three boxes, is composed of the materials concerning Dr. Leach’s publications. There are manuscripts, research materials, correspondence, contracts, and reviews of his books and articles.
Biographical Sketch
Douglas Edward Leach was born in Providence, Rhode Island, 27 May, 1920, the son of Arthur Edward and Saidee Raybold Leach. He graduated Phi Beta Kappa from Brown University in 1942, and from 1942 to 1946 he served as a deck officer in the U.S. Navy. Most of his sea duty was in the Pacific aboard the U.S.S. Elden. Following World War II, he earned his M.A. (1947) and Ph.D. (1952) from Harvard University. He married Brenda Mason in 1950, and the couple had two children, Carol Brenda and Bradford Raybold. Dr. Leach died July 1, 2003 in Nashville.
Leach began his career as a history professor at Bates College, Lewiston, Maine, where he taught from 1950 until 1956. In 1956, he joined the faculty at Vanderbilt University where he remained until his retirement in 1986. Dr. Leach was a leading authority on 17th century colonial American history. His books include Flintlock and Tomahawk: New England in King Philip’s War; The Northern Colonial Frontier, 1607-1763; Arms for Empire: A Military History of the British Colonies in North America, 1607-1763; and Roots of Conflict: British Armed Forces and Colonial America, 1677-1763.
Among his numerous scholarly achievements were Fulbright Lectureships at the Universities of Liverpool, England and Auckland, New Zealand, and the Harvey Branscomb Distinguished Professorship in 1981-1982. He chaired Vanderbilt’s Department of History from 1979 until 1982, and directed the Vanderbilt-in-England Program at the University of Leeds in 1974-1975.
- Box Listing
  - Series I: Correspondence
    - Abbot-Ayers (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bagwell-Bernhard (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biblio-Card Company-Blumstein (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bowden-Harvey Branscomb (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Breen-Byrnes (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cadle-Celona (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chafee-Collins (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cobb-Cowley (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cray-Cushing (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dactrex-Demos (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dick-Duvall (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Eckstein-Ewing (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Fairfield-Freshley (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Fulbright Committee (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Gale-Glasgow (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Glover-Gunderson (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Haakonssen-Hall (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Hamilton-Hazen (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Alexander Heard (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Hedstrom-Hetnal (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Higginbotham-The Historian (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hobbs-Howington (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Hubbard-Hyatt (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Impact ‘65-Israel (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Jacobs-Juricek (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Karsten-Klugman (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Knoll-Kolb (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Kopperman-Kupperman (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Lagemann-Laval (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Leach-Lexington (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Litoff-Lovering-Holman (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - MacKenzie-Matthews (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - McCarley-Meyerhoff (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Michigan Department of State-Morgan (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Samuel Eliot Morison (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Mork-Murdoch (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - National Geographic Society-Navy (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Nelson-Newsweek (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Noldde-Notable American Women (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Obenchain-Orr (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Pang-Phillips (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Piston-Prucha (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Purdy-Pyle (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - David Beers Quinn (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Rao-Riley (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Roberts-Ryan (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Salisbury-Scribner’s Sons (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Sellers-Sittig (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Slotkin-Spriegel (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Starkweather-Swint (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Talbert-TeSelle (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Thelen-Turner (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ultec-United States Air Force (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Vanderbilt-Viall (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Jacque Vogeli (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Wade-Washburn (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Weaver-Whitehall (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Wilby-Wisconsin (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - WJAR TV-Wyatt (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Yantz-Zuccarello (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified correspondents (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Series II: Class Notes, Exams-School-Teaching Materials
    - Sample Footnotes and Bibliography Form Guide (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Microfilms in JUL (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Exams, History 271B (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Exams, History 271B (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Class Notes and Syllabus, History 295 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Class Notes and Syllabus, History 295 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Class Notes, Bibliography, History 305 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Class Notes, History 371A (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Class Notes, History 371B (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Class Notes, History 371B (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Teaching Resources-Historiography (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Teaching Resources-American Indians (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Teaching Resources-Exploration, 986-1504 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Teaching Resources-Spanish and French Empires (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Teaching Resources-English and French Exploration, 1497-1608 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Teaching Resources-New Netherland (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Teaching Resources-Puritan Colonies to, 1676 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Teaching Resources-Virginia to, 1678 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Teaching Resources-Pennsylvania (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Teaching Resources-Westward Movement (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Teaching Resources-Agriculture (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Teaching Resources-Blacks (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Teaching Resources-Militia (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Teaching Resources-Self-Government (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Teaching Resources-Glorious Revolution (1688) (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Teaching Resources-Mercantilism and Commerce (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Teaching Resources-Colonial Press (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Teaching Resources-Great Awakening (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Teaching Resources-Great War for the Empire (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Teaching Resources-England and America, 1760-1775 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Teaching Resources-Greenville Crisis, 1763-1766 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Teaching Resources-Townshend Crisis, 1767-1770 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Teaching Resources-Approach to Revolution, 1770-1774 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Teaching Resources-Struggle for Independence (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Teaching Resources-The United States in the 1780’s (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Teaching Resources-Women’s Experience (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Teaching Resources-Witchcraft (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Teaching Resources-Immigration (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Teaching Resources-Maps for Use in Class (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Teaching Resources-Officer Corps (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Teaching Resources-Historians’ Biographies (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Teaching Resources-Historians’ Biographies (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Teaching Resources-1936 Republican Party Materials (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Series III: Lectures
    - The Growth of Religious Liberty, Bates College Chapel, 3 Dec. 1951 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - The Indian Policy of the Pilgrim Fathers, Society of Mayflower Descendants, Fall, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - The Enjoyment of History, Faculty Round Table (Bates College), 14 Jan. 1954 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Why History? Wranglers, 7 Nov. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Landmarks in American History, 1783 to the Present, Bury Grammar School, England, March 1960 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - George Washington, Nashville Senior Citizens, 22 Feb. 1962 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - King Philip-Front Page News in London, The Rhode Island Historical Society, 18 Nov. 1962 (See also Box 12, Files 7,8,9) (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Training Day in the Colonies, Pattaquamagutt Historical Society, 17 May 1966 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Problems of Intrusive Colonization: America and New Zealand, Victoria University, New Zealand, 27 June 1967 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Sermon for World Communion Sunday, New Zealand, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Military Tradition and Practice in Colonial America, Phi Alpha Theta, The University of Rhode Island, 16 May 1966 and Victoria University, New Zealand, 26 June 1967 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - History Is Fun, West Virginia, April 1969 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Tension, Strife, and Warfare in Early American History, Departmental Seminar, 13 Nov. 1972 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Series of Five Lectures on American History, sponsored by the National Endowment for the Humanities, McCabe Community Center, Nashville, Oct. and Nov. 1973 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - The Declaration of Independence, Leeds, England, Feb. 1975 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - The Declaration of 1776-The Perspective of 1976, Unitarian Church, 18 July 1976 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Aspects of Anglo-American Tension Before 1762, Departmental Seminar, 26 Sept. 1977 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - The Colonial Wars, Taped Lecture for The Voices of America Series, Michael Glazier Inc., 1979 (Manuscript of Tape) (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - The Colonial Wars, Taped Lecture for The Voices of America Series, Michael Glazier Inc., 1979 (Correspondence) (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - The Cartagena Expedition, 1740-42, and Anglo-American Relations, The University of Alabama, 11 Feb. 1983 (Manuscript) See also Box 13, Files 5 & 6. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - The Cartagena Expedition, 1740-42, and Anglo-American Relations, The University of Alabama, 11 Feb. 1983 (Correspondence) (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Composing a Naval Memoir, American Historical Society, 1983 (Manuscript) (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Composing a Naval Memoir, American Historical Society, 1983 (Correspondence) (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - The Royal Navy in the Southern Colonies Before 1763: A Study in Anglo-American Friction, Southern Historical Association, Nov. 1983 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - The Central Pacific Remembered, Vanderbilt University NROTC, 9 Jan. 1986 and 11 Feb. 1988 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Beginnings of the American Naval Tradition, Vanderbilt University NROTC, 29 Jan. 1986 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Untitled lecture delivered at Vine Street Christian Church, 5 Jan. 1988 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - The Puritan Movement, Sunday School Remnant Class, Dec. 1988 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Proposal to the Organization of American Historians for The Second World War: One Man’s Perspective, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - World War II, Nashville Vanderbilt University Alumni Club, 27 Feb. 1992 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - The Origins and Development of the Early American Officer Corps, Vanderbilt University NROTC, 9 April 1992 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - The Importance of World War II in the 20th Century, Kiwanis Club, 3 Sept. 1992 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - The Father of His Country: Chance or Destiny?, Sons of the American Revolution, 23 Feb. 1993 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Remembering the Second World War, Mercer University, 18 April 1994 (Manuscript) (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Remembering the Second World War, Mercer University, 18 April 1994 (Correspondence) (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Indian Relations in American History, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - D.S. Freeman: Virginia Historian, Friend of Washington and Lee, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - The Western Heritage of History, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Series IV: Organizations and Professional Activities
    - Vanderbilt Committee on University Government, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Vanderbilt Committee on University Government, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Vanderbilt Committee on University Government, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Plimoth Plantation-Conference, 6-8 Sept. 1968 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Professional Honors-Fellow, Pilgrim Society, 1974-1990 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Vanderbilt-in-England, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Vanderbilt-in-England, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - New England Tour, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Film Project- George Csicsery’s Project for a Film on King Philip’s War, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Obituary for Forrest Miller, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Vanderbilt- Leave, Spring, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Obituary for Herbert Weaver, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - American Historical Association-Nomination for Honorary Membership of David B. Quinn (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - American Historical Association-Nomination for Honorary Membership of David B. Quinn (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Obituary for Harold Bradley, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Series V: Publications
    - Flintlock and Tomahawk: New England in King Philip’s War (1958)-Research Material (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Flintlock and Tomahawk: New England in King Philip’s War (1958)-Research and Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Flintlock and Tomahawk: New England in King Philip’s War (1958)-Correspondence with Macmillan (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Flintlock and Tomahawk: New England in King Philip’s War (1958)-Correspondence, General (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - The Northern Colonial Frontier, 1607-1763 (1966)-Research Materials and Chapter Outlines (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - The Northern Colonial Frontier, 1607-1763 (1966)- Correspondence with Holt, Rinehart and Winston (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - The Northern Colonial Frontier, 1607-1763 (1966)-Correspondence with Holt, Rinehart, and Winston (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - The Northern Colonial Frontier, 1607-1763 (1966)-Correspondence, General (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Arms for Empire: A Military History of the British Colonies in North America, 1607-1763 (1973)-Contract and Correspondence with Macmillan (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Arms for Empire: A Military History of the British Colonies in North America, 1607-1763-Correspondence with Macmillan (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Arms for Empire: A Military History of the British Colonies in North America, 1607-1763-Correspondence, General (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Arms or Empire: A Military History of the British Colonies in North America, 1607-1763- Reviews (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Roots of Conflict: British Armed Forces and Colonial Americans, 1677-1763 (1986)-Correspondence with The University of North Carolina Press (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Roots of Conflict: British Armed Forces and Colonial Americans, 1677-1763 (1986)-Correspondence, General (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Roots of Conflict: British Armed Forces and Colonial Americans, 1677-1763 (1986)-Reviews (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - A Rhode Islander on King Philip’s War, edited by Douglas Leach (1963)-Manuscript (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - A Rhode Islander on King Philip’s War, edited by Douglas Leach (1963)-Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - A Rhode Islander on King Philip’s War, edited by Douglas Leach (1963)-Reviews (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Benjamin Batten and the London Gazette, New England Quarterly, Spring 1963-Manuscript (See also Box 8, File 7) (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Benjamin Batten and the London Gazette, New England Quarterly, Spring 1963-Research Materials (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Benjamin Batten and the London Gazette, New England Quarterly, Spring 1963-Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - John Gordon, Monograph for the National Park Service (1959)-Manuscript (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - John Gorgon, Monograph for the National Park Service (1959)-Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Rivalry and Warfare: England, France, and Spain (1972)-Manuscript (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Rivalry and Warfare: England, France, and Spain (1972)-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Miles Standish; Benjamin Church; Robert Roger; Sir William Johnson, Articles for the Dictionary of American Military Biography (1979)-Manuscript (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Miles Standish; Benjamin Church; Robert Roger; Sir William Johnson, Articles for the Dictionary of American Military Biography (1979)-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - The Cartagena Expedition, Adapting to Conditions (1986)-Manuscript (See also Box 8, Files 20 & 21) (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - The Cartagena Expedition, Adapting to Conditions (1986)-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Reflections While Moving On, William and Mary Quarterly, July 1988-Manuscript (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Reflections While Moving On, William and Mary Quarterly, July 1988-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Colonial Indian Wars, Handbook of North American Indians (1987)-Manuscript (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Colonial Indian Wars, Handbook of North American Indians (1987)-Draft Manuscript (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Colonial Indian Wars, Handbook of North American Indians (1987)-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - The British Army in America Before 1775, The Blackwell Encyclopedia of the American Revolution (1990)-Manuscript (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - The British Army in America Before 1775, The Blackwell Encyclopedia of the American Revolution (1990)-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - The Colonial Period, Encyclopedia of the American Military, Scribners (1994)-Manuscript (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - The Colonial Period, Encyclopedia of the American Military, Scribners (1994)-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - The Siege of Brookfield (1958)-Unpublished manuscript (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - The Captivity of Mary Rowlandson (1958)-Unpublished Mansucript (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - The Siege of Brookfield and The Captivity of Mary Rowlandson (1958)-Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 18)